It's בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we start today on מ' עמוד ב'.
Mem amud bet. Today's דף Daf is מ"א, Mem alef, but we
are an עמוד Amud behind, but it's actually a pretty quick דף,
Daf, so let's see how well we can do here. And we
start on the משנה, Mishnah, we're going through the different parts of
the animals which are a מום Mum and which are not. So
we pick up on the משנה, Mishnah, first
משנה Mishnah מ' עמוד ב'. Mem amud bet. אוזן הגדי הייתה כפולה,
Ozen hagedi hayeta kfula, so there's a case where the ear of
a deer was doubled over. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara exactly
or whatever what that exactly means. אמרו חכמים בזמן שהוא עצם אחד
מום, Amru chachamim bizman shehu etzem echad mum, if it's one bone,
now an ear doesn't have a bone, so רש"י Rashi says it
means like the cartilage. If it's basically the cartilage folded over and
that causes the ear to fold over, then that's a blemish. בזמן
שאין בו עצם, Bizman she'ein bo etzem, now or there's a different
גרסא Girsa here, either our משנה Mishnah says there is no cartilage
in it, or the other one is ואם אינו עצם אחד, Ve'im
eino etzem echad, if it's not one cartilage but two separate cartilages,
like רש"י Rashi would say rather than a folded over ear but
essentially a separate flap protruding out, then
אינו מום, Eino mum, it's not a blemish. Now what's the difference?
I mean, either way it looks pretty bad, and actually if it's
one cartilage folded over, you might think it's less abnormal than actually
a totally separate cartilage. So if you have אין בו עצם, Ein
bo etzem, no cartilage at all, then you could say maybe we
just view it more like as a flap of skin and it's
not as big of a deal. But for once רש"י Rashi actually
says here
טעמא לא איפרש, Ta'ama lo isparish, the four lines down of the
wide lines of the middle of the line, he says I don't
really get what the difference here is. So he says, but he
says it's at least not as bad as an extra leg because
it's not as visible.
It shows goes רש"י. Rashi.
But exactly, but I think that that expresses the general challenge we've
been having in this פרק, Perek, which is is that there's a
lot of rules but not a lot of like cases
but not a lot of rules. One minute. רבי חנינא בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel omer, Rabbi Gamliel says זנב הגדי שהוא
דומה לשל חזיר, Zanav hagedi shehu domeh leshel chazir, if you have
a tail of a goat that is similar to that of a
pig, ושאין בו שלוש חוליות, Veshe'ein bo shalosh chulyot, and probably should
be or, not and, or doesn't have three vertebrae, then הרי זה
מום, Harei zeh mum, that is a blemish. Again, that would be
an unusual form for the
visible enough and unusual enough for the tail of a goat. Yes.
So if we were to start bring קרבנות, Korbanot, how are we
going to figure these things out? You can't bring קרבן Korban with
them.
There you go. So that's why when we when we figure out
everything else about bringing קרבן, Korban, like exactly where the place of
the קדשי קדשים Kodshei kodashim is and all of that, hopefully we
can also help restore some of these traditions.
Well, I read that there are people who want to bring back
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach even
today because
we can bring it
when everybody's טמא, Tamei, but how can we?
Well, if it has absolutely nothing unusual about it, I mean these
are only questions if it has something unusual and how unusual does
it have to be? Right, if you have something that have nothing
unusual about it, that wouldn't be a problem. But you know, you
can join ישיבת עטרת כהנים Yeshivat Ateret Kohanim and try to, you
know, and try to recapture all of this. But it is, but
look, there's very little בבלי Bavli on it as we've seen. The
גמרא Gemara focuses its discussion on more the things that it, you
know,
has better tradition about than on these things. And, you know, so
right, and there's no ירושלמי Yerushalmi because in general there's no ירושלמי
Yerushalmi about, you know, right, about these things. So, yeah, so I
don't know. All right, let's keep on going. Anyways, see the גמרא,
Gemara, I'm sorry, I just lost the focus a bit, one second.
Why would there why was there no ירושלמי? Yerushalmi?
Well, that's a question whether there was ירושלמי Yerushalmi written on קדשים
Kodashim or not, but we just lost it. The רמב"ם Rambam says
in his הקדמה Hakdama to פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayot that there is
a ירושלמי Yerushalmi קדשים, Kodashim, but nobody has ever had it or
had a manuscript of it even. And then about a hundred years
ago, somebody quote unquote discovered a ירושלמי Yerushalmi קדשים Kodashim and used
it to answer like hundreds of problematic רמב"םs, Rambam and of course
it was discovered to be a forgery. So, anyway, so let's move
on. But so the גמרא Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara says like
this, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, it is a good question, right? You
would think of all of the things the ירושלמי Yerushalmi would want
to discuss the, you know, קדשים, Kodashim, but maybe it was safer
for them to discuss it in בבל Bavel and in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, you know, because, you know, because it was like a
little too close for comfort there. Anyway, it's interesting to think about
that. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, פיו
בלום ורגליו מבולמות. Piv balum veraglav mevulamot. So if the mouth or
the legs are בלום, Balum, what does that mean? רש"י Rashi has
two explanations. One is that it means that basically they are
they're like very narrow, they're not their normal width. The other is
the opposite, it means like blown up, puffed up, swollen, right, exactly.
I'll go with the swollen explanation because it's easier to explain. Anyway,
if it's מחמת הרוח, Machmat haruach, if it is as a result
of, there's a question also what the גרסא Girsa is, רווח Revach
or רוח, Ruach, if it's because of wind, like some type of
a nature, you know, natural cause, like infection or something of that
nature, אינו מום, Eino mum, it's not a blemish. מחמת העצם, Machmat
ha'etzem, if it's that there's the bone is particularly thick or, you
know, and it's deformed actually that way, then הרי זה מום, Harei
zeh mum, then it is. Actually some have the גרסא Girsa of
מחמת עצמו Machmat atzmo as opposed to מחמת הרוח. Machmat haruach. עצם
etzem a bone but it's naturally it's naturally deformed that way. אזניו
כפולות oznav kefulot if its ears are
doubled בחסחוס אחת be-chas-chus achat הרי זה מום harei zeh mum בשתי
חסחוסיות bi-shtei chas-chusiyot אינו מום eino mum it's not and again that's
very bizarre because you would think that that's certainly a deformity so
this is where Rashi says I don't know what the reason is.
All right, רבן גמליאל אמר Rabban Gamliel amar now we're going to
get to an area that's a little easier to discuss. זנב הגדי
שהוא דומה לשל חזיר zenav ha-gedi she-hu domeh le-shel chazir if the
goat's tail is like that of a pig. אמר רב פפא amar
Rav Pappa לא תימא דקטינא lo teima de-katina not doesn't only mean
that it's small like a pig, a pig has a very small
short tail, אלא דכריכא אף על גב דאלימא ela de-kericha af al
gav de-alima even if it's its normal sort of thickness or size
if it's rounded then it's that's enough like a pig. Now what
does rounded mean? So Rashi says that's what I assumed it meant,
right, that it's curled. Right, that's exactly what I assumed. Right, right,
that's exactly what I assumed. Rashi says what it also means is
that a pig the you know the circumference of the tail is
more circular than that of other animals where the circumference is more
oblong. So that's what Rashi says but I also I assumed it
meant curled. Okay, now we go on. או שאין בו שלש חוליות.
o she-ein bo shalosh chulyot. Okay,
or if it does not have three vertebrae. אמר רב הונא amar
Rav Huna בגדי שתים הרי זה מום be-gedi shtayim harei zeh mum
even though it says that it needs to have
three vertebrae, here's really the story, if it's a goat then if
it has two well two vertebrae it's a מום, mum, שלש shalosh
three אינו מום. eino mum. That's that's a minimum amount of vertebrae.
ובטלה u-ve-taleh by a sheep it's one more. שלש הרי זה מום
shalosh harei zeh mum three is already too abnormal, ארבע אינו מום
arba eino mum four is already within the range of of normality
and that's okay. Four vertebrae. מתיבי meitivei I'll ask you, we have
a ברייתא braita that says the that says it's one degree more
more strict. בגדי אחת הרי זה מום be-gedi achat harei zeh mum
by a goat only one vertebra is a מום, mum, שתים אינו
מום shtayim eino mum two is already normal enough. ובטלה שתים הרי
זה מום u-ve-taleh shtayim harei zeh mum by a sheep it's two
is a problem or a מום mum actually, it's good but anyway
two is a מום, mum, שלש אינו מום shalosh eino mum three
is not. So you see you said you needed it to be
here actually oh actually this is more lenient right because no this
is more strict. It's only a blemish if it has one fewer
vertebrae than you said. So here we see that it's a blemish
is one and two, you said two and three. So the גמרא
Gemara says תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא. tiyuvta de-Rav Huna tiyuvta.
So that is a contradiction of Rav Huna that said that the
amount was for a מום mum was three and four, here we're
saying it's two and three is the minimum. So the גמרא Gemara
says רב הונא מתניתין אתעייא. Rav Huna matnitin it-aya. Rav Huna was
was made to err because of the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah
misled him or he was misled by the משנה. Mishnah. אי הוא
סבר מדרישא בגדי ei hu savar mi-reisha be-gedi right the משנה Mishnah
says that if it doesn't have three vertebrae it's a מום. mum.
So he figured what animal are we talking about? Since originally we
were talking about about a goat because it talked about the ear
folded over, סיפא נמי בגדי סיפא נמי בגדי seifa nami be-gedi the
end is also about a goat. ולא היא ולא היא ve-lo hi
it's not true. רישא בגדי וסיפא בטלה רישא בגדי וסיפא בטלה reisha
be-gedi ve-seifa be-taleh the beginning was a goat and the end we're
talking about a sheep. When we say explicitly goat we mean goat,
otherwise the default is sheep. So anyway that's where he got his
mistake, not obvious at all. Now you understand why he made a
very an honest mistake. All right, moving on. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
אומר Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos says notice
again you know it's the more obscure תנאים Tannaim that we're coming
across. יבלת בעיניו יבלת בעיניו yavelet be-einav
that something has a יבלת yavelet which is some type of like
a a growth that protrudes coming out of its eye. ושנפגם עצם
ידו ורגלו ושנפגם עצם ידו ורגלו ve-she-nifgam etzem yado ve-raglo
or its arm or leg was nicked. Before we spoke about broken,
so here ושנפרק עצמו של פיו ושנפרק עצמו של פיו ve-she-nifrak atzmo
shel piv
or if the bone of the mouth was was was like loosened
or taken off. What does that mean? Rashi says it means the
gums. So the gums you know before we spoke about a tooth,
you would think gums is a bigger מום, mum, but gums are
more hidden, they're basically completely hidden by by the lips. So therefore
by the gums it's not enough of a small injury, it basically
has to be you know taken out or detached I think is
a better word. And those would be a מום. mum. That's his
statement. Not clear if anybody argues on that, we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara. עינו אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה עינו אחת גדולה
ואחת קטנה eino achat gedola ve-achat ketana
now Michael was asking about this yesterday. Yesterday we talked about about
misshapen you know disproportionate limbs but we only talked about it in
terms of the thigh or the shoulder. Here we're talking about all
a range of limbs. One eye is big or one eye is
too small. אזנו אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה אזנו אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה
ozno achat gedola ve-achat ketana or one is bigger than normal one
is smaller. במראה be-mareh now that's only if it's visibly different. ולא
במידה ve-lo be-mida you don't go take out a ruler and you
decide oh this is 2.8 inches and this is 2.9 inches. Okay,
that's not enough to be enough of a difference and enough of
a deformity. But if it's visibly different sizes that is a מום.
mum. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer שתי ביצים שתי ביצים shtei
beitzim if it's when we're back to now the testicles אחת גדולה
כשתים שבחברתה אחת גדולה כשתים שבחברתה achat gedola ki-shtayim she-be-chavertah if one
is twice as big as the other that is also a
מום. mum. ולא הודו חכמים ולא הודו חכמים ve-lo hodu chachamim they
didn't agree because again that is less visible although you Really the
question is
we're talking about not talking about what it looks the scrotum, we're
talking about the actual testicles. Okay, not that the scrotum itself is
deformed, presumably that he might agree to. למימרא Lememra so the גמרא
Gemara says this seems to say דיבלת הוי מומא deyavelet havei muma
this יבלת yavelet which is again some type of a like of
a growth that it comes out of the body, that's a blemish.
ורמינהו Ureminhu I'll ask you on this ואלו שאין שוחטין עליהם לא
במקדש ולא במדינה ve'elu she'ein shochtin aleihem lo bamikdash velo bamedinah and
now we are going to get and we're going to see this
in the משנה Mishna on the next דף daf today's דף daf
actually hopefully we get to it, that the exact category of something
that falls midpoint. It's not enough of a מום mum that you
can שחט shacht it outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but it's
a big enough problem that you can't bring it as a קרבן.
korban. It's not תמים tamim but it's not a מום, mum, okay,
and it falls right in the middle. So it's the worst case
scenario. And here it says here are those that fall into that
category. בעל גרב ובעל יבלת Ba'al garav uva'al yavelet if it has
these types of scabs or a יבלת yavelet again some type of
a protrusion of a growth of skin, that these are midpoint, that
these you can't bring as a קרבן korban but you can שחט.
shacht. So how does our משנה Mishna say that a יבלת yavelet
is a מום mum that you can שחט shacht on the basis
of it? So now the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא vatisbra one minute,
let me even ask you before if that whole thing makes sense.
והכתיב veha-ketiv it's explicit in the פסוקים pesukim that a יבלת yavelet
is a blemish. And again here we are borrowing
conflating from בכור Bechor and other קרבנות. korbanos. What does it say
in the תורה? Torah? יבלת, Yavelet, it says או גרב או יבלת,
o garav o yavelet, right, it says explicitly גרב garav and a
יבלת yavelet are a blemish. So now we got a problem. The
משנה Mishna later says it's only midpoint, we have a פסוק pasuk
that says it's a complete blemish, and our משנה Mishna says it's
a blemish when you have it on the eye. So let's take
a look.
In the eye is a blemish also.
Well that's exactly what we're going to see. Let's take a look.
אלא לא קשיא Ella lo kashya so we're going to try a
couple of answers. הא בגופא הא בעיינא. Ha begufa ha be'ayna. First
of all difference between the body and the eye. In the eye
it's much more visible, it looks it's much more disfiguring, so the
eye it's a blemish, that's our משנה, Mishna, that's the פסוק, pasuk,
where it's only a midpoint, not a full blemish but not perfect,
that is on the rest of the body.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, that's still I think there
should be a problem because if it's a growth it's visible.
Okay, so let's take a look Michael, all the things you're going
to have to I'm sure are in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מכדי Michdi
one minute, קרא סתמא כתיב, kra stama ketiv, the פסוק pasuk says
without any distinction that it's a מום. mum. How can you say
the whole פסוק pasuk is only talking about the eye? מה לי
בגופא מה לי בעיינא, ma li begufa ma li be'ayna, what difference
does it make if the body or the eye, the פסוק pasuk
says straight that יבלת yavelet is a מום. mum. אלא לא קשיא
Ella lo kashya so that's difficult. הא דאית ביה עצם הא דלית
ביה עצם. Ha de'is bei etzem ha deleis bei etzem. So it's
whether there's a bone in it or there's not. If it's not
a bone in it then it's just like a skin flap. A
skin flap is no big deal, but if it actually is some
protrusion of skin and bone, then that obviously is some real disfigurement.
So bone in the משנה Mishna to יבלת yavelet in the eye
means there's a bone?
Well let's take a look. Okay,
so let's take a look. דקרא, Dekra, the פסוק pasuk that says
it's always a problem, דאית ביה עצם, de'is bei etzem, has a
bone. מתניתין, Masnisin, דלית ביה עצם, deleis bei etzem, our two משניות
Mishnayos is it's just a skin flap without a bone. So and
there it makes a difference eye or the rest of the body.
ובעיינא, Uve'ayna, in the eye, which is our משנה, Mishna, הוי מומא,
havei muma, that's very disfiguring even if it's just a skin flap.
בגופא, Begufa, in the body, לא הוי מומא, lo havei muma, it's
not a blemish and that's the next משנה. Mishna.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, that's very nice, but if
it's all it is is a skin flap, then I would question
if it's a problem at all. ולית ליה עצם, Veleis lei etzem,
if it has no bone, בגופא פסולה, begufa pesula, it would be
a problem in the body? I mean yes I admit in the
eye it would be very disfiguring, but if you just had a
skin flap on the rest of the body without would that you
actually call a blemish? הרי טילטול בעלמא הוא, harei tiltul be'alma hu,
it's just like a little skin flap, what's the big deal? Which
again raises the question all along, which is how do you define
perfect, how do you define blemish, how disfiguring, what are your not
only what's your range of like normal, which is a question, but
also like what types of things do you even pay attention to?
I mean you don't say if the color is a little bit
off it's a מום, mum, right? So I mean what types of
things are considered significant enough or disfiguring enough? So anyway here the
גמרא. Gemara.
A יבלת yavelet is a wart. Wart, okay. A wart is very
different than a skin flap.
Well I said like a skin protrusion, but
yeah.
A wart is colored, right,
often textured disfiguration. Skin flap I would think is
a piece
of skin that
covers that like protrudes and whatever. Also you have a bone in
a wart? I mean I don't know if you have a bone
in a skin flap either. No, no, no. I don't know, it's
obviously some protrusion of skin, okay, but the fact the גמרא Gemara
says without a bone the גמרא Gemara calls it like a skin
flap, that's what a טילטול tiltul is. So that's why I've been
calling it that.
What happens to this animal that it's not the one that's not
considered?
The same thing that happens with one that has no מום mum
at all, you have to wait till it gets a מום mum
and until that point you can't do anything with it.
So they're trying to be strict even though the תורה Torah says
if it has this יבלת yavelet whatever it is.
Right, they're trying to say that's true, meaning if they're
not all יבלת yavelet are not all the same. Right.
What is behind it?
Yeah, I, you know again, I don't know, I mean...
Because it makes things harder and a greater monetary loss for...
Well, I said it was too bad you weren't here yesterday where
we had a whole argument between Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri where Rabbi Akiva said עד מתי אתה מכלה ממונם של ישראל.
ad matai ata mechaleh mamonam shel Yisrael. So there is that attitude
that is expressed. I, you know, I don't know. Obviously, on the
other hand, there's some things that they call a מום mum that
aren't mentioned at all in the תורה Torah that you wouldn't have
ever expected, like a slightly deformed tail or something. So I, you
know, I'm not sure. That's always a question of just how much
are your decisions informed by those sort of, you know, the sort
of practical implications and how much are they by your conceptual models
that you're bringing to it. Like if this is just a flap,
so do you really call it a מום? mum?
You know, so I mean, it, you know, those issues about what
are, how does this affect real people, you know, is part of
the decision-making process which came up yesterday with Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri. But I'm just saying I think that they're also
trying to have a sense of honesty to what they think, you
know, conceptually a מום mum is about, and something that's so trivial
like a flap, you know, on the other hand, like I said,
there are things that aren't in the פסוקים pesukim at all that
they said are מומים. mumim. So I'm not sure you can sort
of determine a consistent pattern about that. All right, so let's see.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Oh, just one second, sorry. Just about this משנה. mishnah. It seems
that the Steinzaltz is saying the exact opposite of רש"י, Rashi, I
think, with the גדי gedi with the מין אוזן. min ozen. רש"י
Rashi is saying I think it all has like one. Yeah. So
he's saying just the opposite, ששיש עצם אחד sheyesh etzem echad which
means a separate like ear has its own bone. That's what he's
saying.
Aha. That's interesting. Okay. Certainly not what רש"י Rashi said. But then
how does he read שתי עצמות? shte etzamot? Anyway. Okay, so let's
see. Right, which is what the גמרא Gemara says, and that's not
a problem. Anyway, so let's take a look. גמרא Gemara says like
this, back to where we are.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תילתולא באדם הוא דתנן, tiltula be'adam
hu detnan, רבי אליעזר אומר בעלי התילתולין פסולין באדם וכשרים בבהמה. Rabbi
Eliezer omer ba'alei hatiltulin pesulin be'adam u'ksherim bivehema.
People with skin flaps is a problem for כהנים, kohanim, but it's
not good, but for animals, it's totally not problematic. So this also
a question raised yesterday, right? What standard do כהנים kohanim go by?
And here you see we've had two standards, right? One was enough
of a מום mum that you would שחט shacht a קרבן korban
outside בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. The other was a big enough problem
not to bring it as a קרבן. korban. And here we see
that the כהנים kohanim standard is even higher than that, that even
something that the animal would be totally כשר kasher with would be
a problem for a כהן kohen because by there it's much less
about the way the גמרא Gemara frames it by a כהן, kohen,
it's much less about the idea of מום mum and much more
about the idea of like within a certain limited band of quote-unquote
normalcy, שוה בזרעו של אהרן. shaveh bezaro shel Aharon.
So even if you can't even call it a blemish, you know,
that is more closer to what the גמרא's Gemara idea before was
about תמים tamim by the animal. So here you have the כהנים
kohanim have even a higher standard even than just an animal bringing
as a קרבן, korban, let alone a מום. mum. Anyway, you see
that it's okay by a קרבן, korban, so how could you say
that's a problem? אלא אידי ואידי בעיניו. Ela idi ve'idi be'einav. Okay,
fine, it's both about the eye. ולא קשיא הא בשחר הא בלבן.
Velo kashya ha beshachar ha belavan. That when is it a, when
does the תורה Torah say it's a problem, or
let me again, the תורה Torah still that it has a bone.
When in our משנה mishnah is it a, what is the difference
about whether it is or is not a problem? It's they both
could be in the eye, which is more disfiguring, but the difference
is whether it's the black of the eye or the white of
the eye. So the גמרא Gemara says and the white of the
eye as we said before is less of a problem. והא אין
מומים בלבן. Veha ein mumim belavan. One minute, presumably there are no
blemishes in the white of the eye, which is again so bizarre,
right? I mean, it's disfiguring, why shouldn't it be a problem? Why
is the eye special that the white of the eye is excluded?
And that's the issue we raised before. I mean, you know, there
by the eye it particularly focuses on a particular מום mum that
the תורה Torah mentions by an eye, תבלול בעינו, tavlul be'eino, and
wants to define it very narrowly. What is precisely defined as the
eye? But why isn't it part of a more generic category of
disfiguring things?
Anyway, yeah, so the white of the eye can often have a
marking in it and maybe they just assume it could be more
natural.
Maybe, but this isn't a mark, it's a skin flap and the
גמרא Gemara sort of takes a categorical approach, אין מומים בלבן. ein
mumim belavan. Okay, now the question is how we read the next
line, whether the גמרא Gemara steps back from that. So here's what
the גמרא Gemara says. So again, the תורה's Torah case is that
there's a bone in it. How comes our משנה's mishnah distinguish between
whether these flaps are or are not a full מום? mum? אלא
אידי ואידי. Ela idi ve'idi. Now תוספות Tosafot is, here it says
בלבן, belavan, but תוספות Tosafot is גורס gores is בשחר, beshachar, because
תוספות Tosafot wants to be consistent with the statement before that the
white is never a problem. So תוספות Tosafot reads it, you're right,
they're both in the black of the eye. ואמר ריש לקיש לא
קשיא הא דאית ביה שיער הא דלית ביה שיער. Ve'amar Reish Lakish
lo kashya ha de'it bei se'ar ha delait bei se'ar. Is there
hair growing out of this skin? As there's a piece of skin,
I don't know how skin grows out of the eye altogether, okay,
so skin
grows out of that
and then hair grows out of that.
I don't, right, I don't get it at all.
But that's really disfiguring. Anyway, that's what תוספות Tosafot reads. רש"י Rashi
reads that it's like our גירסא, girsa, it's in the white. So
according to רש"י, Rashi, this principle that there is no מום mum
in the white of the eye is at least not completely categorical.
Okay, yeah, so the תוספות's Tosafot case is that there is a
flap in the eye and then based on if there's hair growing
out of it? If there's just hair, if there's just a flap
growing out of the black, that's not a problem?
It's not, you can't bring it as a קרבן, korban, but it's
not a מום mum to שחט shacht on it. I don't know,
I don't know, I cannot say for sure. Yeah. These are all
questions of how bad it is, but I don't get it. רש"י's
Rashi גרסא girsa is better at least because I don't understand why
the white should be categorically excluded. But I also don't understand how
you can get skin growing out of an eye.
Anyway, at least the way I understand, maybe it like kind of
goes to the side a little bit too much, cause like you
know, the edge of the white, you know?
Yeah, so you mean whether it gets into the eye but it
comes from outside? Maybe, yes. Charlie?
So there are certain types of tumors that grow on the eye.
Oh, that's interesting. They're not very common, but I just looked it
up. Oh, wow. I've heard of that. Wow. They even occur in
humans, too.
Wow. Does hair ever come out of them? I don't know. Possibly.
Okay, let's move
on. אחת גדולה. achat gedola. תנא. Tana. גדולה כשל עגל, gedola keshel
egel, if it's as big as that of a cow, that would
be a problem if this is happening in a sheep. Or קטנה,
ketana, if it's small, כשל אווז, keshel avaz, like a duck. Either
that would be too big or too small. Now, I want to
say, by the way, that that's not necessarily פשט pshat in the
משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna seems to say אחת גדולה ואחת
קטנה
achat gedola veachat
ketana
means they're disproportionate to one another, whereas the ברייתא braita seems to
be reading it as if one is either bigger than normal or
smaller than normal, and then wants to say how big is considered
too big and how small is considered too
small. Yes, Charlie? Charlie, what do you want to say?
It is the most common tumor in bovines.
Oh, look at that. Of that... something in the eye?
Ocular melanoma.
And what happens? It's like actually like some skin is protrudes?
It is
a plaque, a small circular white elevation on the surface of the
eye.
Wow. Well that might sound like the גמרא Gemara before about the
white spot that
the גמרא Gemara talked about. Or a dermatoid is a hard raised
growth on the eyelids as opposed to the eye itself. Interesting.
A papilloma, which is a wart-like growth.
Oh, a wart-like growth!
We need a vet in this...
yeah. All right, we do.
Does anybody
know of a big eyes...
actually my sister-in-law's a vet.
That's exactly what I understood. Right, right. I agree with... yeah.
Who's the vet? David Bestler. Get him in here!
Where is he?
He goes to Chabad. Okay.
All right. Okay, וייטער. veiter.
Okay, אוזן אחת גדולה, ozen achat gedola, misshaped ears. רבנן עד כמה?
Rabbanan ad kama? So now we're going on the point about the
testicles where it was two and one ratio was not enough for
the Rabbis. So what stage would the Rabbis admit that it actually
would be a מום? mum? תניא, Tanya, אלו המומים אפילו אינו לשני
אלא כפול כשרה, elu hamumim afilu eino lishni ela kefol keshera, even
if the second testicle's only as small as like a bean, that
would still not be a problem, so maybe they would not say
it would be a מום mum at all if they are misshaped.
But again, what's the Rabbis' definition? They disagreed with the fact one
side of
it was two to
one, the size of the testicles, it was a מום mum and
the Rabbis disagreed. So and they're saying? They're saying presumably it doesn't
matter how small it is.
Okay, let's take a look.
Next Mishna. Wait, sorry, very quick question.
We saw with the eyes, so are we saying that if they're
disproportionate, then it's not a problem? But if they're both really small?
I understand what you're saying. The משנה Mishna sounds like one thing,
the גמרא Gemara sounds like another.
I... how do we פסקן? pasken? I don't know. No, I mean
both are small, like a duck.
I understand. I understand.
I think that makes the difference between the way the משנה Mishna
read it and the ברייתא braita in the גמרא. Gemara. The משנה
Mishna sounds like it means disproportionate to one another and the ברייתא
braita in the גמרא Gemara sounds like it means smaller than an
average.
So I don't know the answer to that.
But I mean the one is still... I understood, I understood the
question. Let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishna. זנב העגל
שאינה מגעת לערכוב. Zanav ha-egel she-eina magaat l'arkov. Now if you have
the tail of a calf that does not reach the ערכוב, arkov,
which we'll see is like the knee. אמרו חכמים כל מרבית עגלים
כך הן. Amru Chachamim kol marbit agalim kach hen. And now it's
actually quite fascinating because now they actually talk about the norm of
distribution and they say this is the norm of all of like
the calves. כל זמן שהם מגדילות הן נמתחות. Kol zman sheheim magdilot
hen nimtachot. As long as they grow, the tail continues to stretch
out. But presumably the way רש"י Rashi at least reads it is
that they're not disagreeing, they're agreeing. They're saying that it starts as
long as getting up to the knee joint and then it continues
to grow. And so therefore anything that's not within that normal range
would be a מום. mum. So רש"י Rashi reads it as an
agreement, not a disagreement. איזו היא ערכוב? Eizu hi arkov? What's the
ערכוב? arkov? שאמרו, sheamru, רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben
Antignos omer, בערכוב שבאמצע הירך. ba-arkov she-be-emtza ha-yarech. The knee in the
middle of the joint, which is basically what we'd call the knee
as opposed to the cows have one closer to the foot, which
for us would be the ankle, for them it's a little higher
up. But anyway, we're talking about the knee. תנא. Tana. Finally top
of today's actual official דף. daf. כף העליון ולא כף התחתון. kaf
ha-elyon v'lo kaf ha-tachton. The upper joint, not the lower joint. וכנגדו
בגמל ניכר. ukenegdo b'gamal nikar. And by camels in particular you really
see where the leg is jointed in that area. When we were
learning חולין Chullin we had a picture of that and you could
really see it by camels. Okay, but we're moving on. על אלו
מומים שוחטין את הבכור. Al elu mumim shochtin et ha-bechor. Now we
have a nice wrap-up משנה. Mishna. On all the מומים mumim we
mentioned before you can check the בכור bechor and ופסולי המוקדשין נפדין
עליהם. u-psulei ha-mukdashin nifdin aleihem. If it happened by קרבנות, korbanot, it's
enough of a מום mum to redeem it. So this משנה Mishna
basically says they're really all the same, the definition of the מום,
mum, which has been implicit, but it does raise questions at the
beginning of the פרק perek because of the... the other, the other
קרבנות korbanot which were much more detailed. So it's quite interesting why
the גמרא gemara all along has been ignoring the פסוקים pesukim primarily,
mostly ignoring the פסוקים pesukim that exist by the other, other קדשים
kodashim since here it seems to be putting them all in the
same category. Let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. הא תו
למה לי? Ha tu lama li? Why do I need this wrap
up משנה? mishna? התנא ליה רישא? Ha'tana lei reisha? We already על
אלו מומין שוחטין את הבכור. Al elu mumim shochtin et ha-bechor. That's
how our משנה, mishna, פרק perek begins. These are the blemishes you
שחט shacht בכור. bechor. No, סיפא איצטריך. Seifa itzterich. ופסולי המוקדשים נפדים
עליהם. U'psulei hamukdashim nifdim aleihem. No, to tell you exactly what we've
been saying, that it's the same הלכה halacha for בכור bechor and
for other קרבנות. korbanot. So the גמרא gemara says הא נמי פשיטא.
Ha nami peshita. That's also obvious. מדשחטינן מפרק מבעיא? Mide'shachtinan mifrak mibaya?
If you can שחט shacht without redeeming, right, that's the big חידוש
chiddush of a בכור bechor that with a מום mum you can
שחט shacht even though it has the same קדושה. kedusha. So of
course you could redeem by another קרבן. korban. Now again, that's only
obvious if you assume that they're basically the same category, right? I
mean the תורה Torah says one thing by a בכור bechor and
another thing by קרבנות, korbanot, but the גמרא gemara here takes it
for granted that the same concept of מום mum should apply to
both. Okay, so again, it would have been very interesting though to
explore more directly the פסוקים pesukim it says by the other קרבנות
korbanot which the גמרא gemara has not really done anyway. So the
גמרא gemara says it's obvious it's the same הלכה. halacha. אלא איידי
דתנא שלוש אוסיף. Ela aidei de'tana shalosh osif. Since we said yesterday,
right, that this אילא Ila added three other מומים. mumim. ואמרו לו
לא שמענו. Ve'amru lo lo shamanu. And the rabbis said we haven't,
we don't have a tradition about this. לא שמענו את אלו. Lo
shamanu et elu. ודתני ואתי דיחידאה. Ve'detani ve'ati deyichida'ah. And then afterwards
we have some משניות mishnayot that are said in the name of
individual opinions, רב חנינה בן אנטיגנוס, Rav Chanina ben Antignos, even though
we don't have explicitly mentioned a debate. דכססנהו בכולהו, De'kasasnehu be'chulehu, על
אלו מומין שוחטין את הבכור ופסולי המוקדשים נפדים עליהם. Al elu mumim
shochtin et ha-bechor u'psulei hamukdashim nifdim aleihem. That's why we have this
wrap up to tell you that even though there's some other opinions
were mentioned as individual opinions, really we all agree about it all,
other than that one little debate we had before, which even then
we said that the later בית דין Beit Din came around to
his position. So really therefore to tell you that all of these
positions are really consensus. Again, except for the explicit ones which are
mentioned to have been in debate. But even the ones that are
mentioned in the name of individuals are really are the consensus. Okay,
and now we move to this interesting middle category where it's enough
of a problem not to bring it as a קרבן korban but
not enough of a problem to שחט shacht on it. ואלו שאין
שוחטין עליהם, Ve'elu she'ein shochtin aleihem, לא במקדש ולא במדינה. Lo ba'mikdash
ve'lo ba'medina. You can't שחט shacht in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
It's not perfect enough to שחט shacht in the בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash, but it's not enough of a מום mum to שחט shacht
outside the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. And now it's some of these
are variations of what we said before and some of them are
totally new categories. Let's take a look. חברור והמים שאינן קבועים. Chavarur
ve'hamayim she'einan kvuim. So there's חברור, chavarur, this like white, what was
that again? White spots and water that is not fixed, meaning right
now it has this problem but it is not seen as permanent.
And really that can be generalized, right? Rashi said white spots in
the eye. That really can be generalized to any מום עובר, mum
over, right, any transitory blemish. You can't שחט shacht on the basis
of it, but while it has the blemish, you can't bring it
as a קרבן. korban. Okay, so a transitory blemish puts you right
in the middle. You can't bring it and you can't שחט. shacht.
והחטין הפנימיות שנפגמו אבל לא שנעקרו. Ve'hachittin hapnimiyot she'nifgemu aval lo she'ne'ekru.
The inner molars that were, or the roots of the molars that
were damaged or nicked, but they weren't completely uprooted. Now that's interesting
because presumably we said where they were, when there were those damages
on the inner molars they were not visible. If they're not visible,
so again, is this a definition of תמים, tamim, that it doesn't
have to be a מום, mum, it's enough of a problem that
it's not תמים, tamim, it's a different standard for bringing it as
a קרבן, korban, not just the absence of מום? mum? Or is
it a different standard of what visible means? Maybe under certain circumstances
it's visible, and maybe it's a different standard when it comes to
bringing it as a קרבן. korban. ובעל גרב ובעל יבלת. U'ba'al garav
u'ba'al yabbelet. This is what we quoted before. People, different types of
scabs or warts or skin flaps. ובעל חזזית, U'ba'al chazazit, another type
of a wart. All of those are not perfect enough as a
קרבן, korban, but they're not a big enough problem to be a
מום. mum. Okay, and we said that that was on the body,
not on the eye. Now we get a totally different category. זקן,
Zaken, not thinking about physical deformities but just about things about how
appropriate is it to be brought as a קרבן. korban. זקן, Zaken,
if it's very old, וחולה, Ve'choleh, or it's sick, ומזוהם, U'mezoham, it's
smelly. Yeah, well these come up very regularly. ושנעבדה בו עבירה. Ve'sheneevdah
bo aveira. It was, a sin was done with it, which means
it was an act of bestiality. ושהמית את האדם, Ve'shehemit et ha'adam,
or it killed somebody, it gored somebody. And the last two is
על פי עד אחד או על פי בעלים, Al pi ed echad
o al pi be'alim, that you only have one witness or the
owners attest to it. Why? Because if you have two witnesses, then
you put the animal to death and they're forbidden in benefit, so
you don't even have to say that they're not a קרבן. korban.
You wouldn't even have the animal around if you only have one
witness. Exactly, but if you only have one witness or the owners,
you're actually
allowed to שחט shacht it and get
benefit from it, but you cannot use it as a קרבן. korban.
וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס. Ve'tumtum ve'androgynos. And if it has a טומטום, tumtum, which
is that it has both, the טומטום tumtum is that the genitalia
are covered up, and an אנדרוגינוס androgynos is androgynous, so it has
male... but it's not a מום mum enough that you can שחט
shecht it outside. רבי ישמעאל אומר Rabbi Yishmael omer side-switch it, רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says, אין לך מום גדול מזה. Ein lacha mum
gadol mizeh. If it's an אנדרוגינוס, androgynus, טומטום tumtum we'll discuss, but
at least an אנדרוגינוס, androgynus, there's no bigger blemish than this. Meaning,
if it is a male, which is what it would have to
be by a בכור, bechor, and it still has also genitalia of
female, that is a big enough deformity that that's a מום. mum.
Okay, so that's what he says. וחכמים אומרים, V'Chachamim omrim, אינו בכור
אלא ניגזז ונעבד. eino bechor ela nigzaz v'ne'avad. They're even more lenient.
They say it's not a בכור, bechor, you know why? Because it's
not a male. And then, they're not necessarily saying it's a female,
maybe it's a third category. Okay, what it's not and actually somebody
just told me that I have a friend who's an optometrist and
you know he sees a lot of people and anyway so one
person came in who actually was transgendered and you know so she
was born a he, now's a she, but on his form that
he has to fill out he has male, female and other. And
he actually said he actually had to check other. So anyway, so
this is, I mean I'm serious about this that people that are
into gender identity very like the idea that the גמרא Gemara spends
time discussing אנדרוגינוס androgynus and the possibility of a third gender. So
anyway, what did transgender? What? Someone's going to say, so born a
man is now a right but when that man became a woman
that's when the person checked other? Well she was I think she
was pre-op. She hadn't but it doesn't matter because from a medical
perspective he had to know that this person was taking all these
hormones or whatever in order to maintain this appearance, so it was
important just medically to understand that.
I mean he called her she, you know, treated whatever gender she
wanted to
identify with, but from the
medical perspective he had to know. Anyway, he considers himself as a
third category. Well some do, definitely.
Right, exactly. That, so there's like interesting gender politics around this. But
let me just spell out what the debate is. So the first
opinion says it's a male or possibly a male but not definitely
a מום, mum, so therefore you're in this middle category and can't
do anything. The second one says no, no, no, it's a male
with a מום mum or at least even if it is a
male it's definitely a מום mum and
therefore you can שחט, shecht, it's a male with a מום, mum,
but it still has קדושת בכור kedushas bechor because it might be
a male. And the third one says it doesn't even have קדושת
בכור, kedushas bechor, you can shear it, you can work it, it's
not a male, end of story. Yes, Charlie. This is the issue
of transgenders is a real issue because there are Jews who have
had sex-change operations. Right. And I actually was at a מנין minyan
with one recently. Yeah, there's a lot of interesting הלכה halacha around
for example. Okay, I'm not going to get into this discussion but
that is, alright, moving on. When when this started when I was
a kid and this started happening, sex-change operations, we used to make
jokes about it. Oh, so could the person count to a מנין?
minyan? Anyway, now these are real real הלכות. halachos. Yeah, yeah. Alright,
anyway, moving on. דגרב לא, D'garav lo, so we'll get to all
that fun in a minute if you let me get there. So,
דגרב לא, D'garav lo, so you telling me that a wart is
not a מום? mum? והכתיב גרב באורייתא, v'haksiv garav b'Orayta, the תורה
Torah says גרב, garav, whatever that is, some type of a wart
in the תורה. Torah. But we're dealing with שבלו. she-belo. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says וחזזית לא. v'chazazis lo. And now וחזזית והכתיב
ילפת באורייתא, v'chazazis v'haksiv yallefes b'Orayta, it says ילפת yallefes and we're
going to say that ילפת yallefes is a חזזית. chazazis. דתניא גרב
זה החרס, D'tanya garav zeh hacheres, so it says גרב garav that's
חרס cheres which is some type of very dry wart. ילפת זו
חזזית מצרית Yallefes zu chazazis mitzris and the ילפת yallefes is the
Egyptian חזזית. chazazis. So you see the same things in the תורה
Torah are mentioned in the משנה. Mishna. Why are they not a
מום? mum? ואמר ריש לקיש למה נקרא שמה ילפת? V'amar Reish Lakish
lama nikra shemo yallefes? Why is it called ילפת? yallefes? שמלפפת והולכת
עד יום המיתה, Shemelapefes v'holeches ad yom hamisa, because it like, you
know, it sort of cleaves to you, it licks on you, it
adheres to you until the day of death. Not very pleasant. So
anyway, you see these are really problematic. So why does our משנה
Mishna say they're not? בשלמא חזזית אחזזית לא קשיא כאן בחזזית המצרית
כאן בחזזית דעלמא. Bishlama chazazis achazazis lo kashya, kan b'chazazis hamitzris, kan
b'chazazis d'alma. חזזית chazazis isn't the problem because חזזית chazazis is our
translation of the word ילפת yallefes in the תורה, Torah, but that
might be what we specifically called it which was the Egyptian חזזית.
chazazis. Maybe the חזזית chazazis in our משנה Mishna is less severe
and therefore it's not a problem. אלא גרב אגרב קשיא. Ela garav
agarav kashya. But you really do have a problem. The תורה Torah
says גרב garav is not an issue, is a מום, mum, and
our משנה Mishna says גרב garav is not an issue. So the
גמרא Gemara says גרב אגרב נמי לא קשיא הא בלח הא ביבש.
Garav agarav nami lo kashya, ha belach ha beyavesh. The תורה's Torah's
גרב garav where it's a מום mum is dry, which is sort
of like really either disfiguring or really permanent, and ours is with
a moist wart which presumably can heal. לח מצטייא, Lach mitztaya, a
moist one will heal. יבש לא מצטייא, Yavesh lo mitztaya, a dry
one won't heal. So therefore in our משנה Mishna it's not a
problem because it's not permanent. So the גמרא Gemara says ולח מצטייא?
V'lach mitztaya? A moist one can heal? והכתיב, v'haksiv, it says, יככה
ה' בשחין מצרים ובעפולים ובגרב ובילפת. Yakecha Hashem b'shchin Mitzrayim u'vafolim u'vagarav
u'veyallef. יאלפת, yalefet, thank you, וביאלפת. uvalafet. So anyway, it says גרב,
garev, and it says אשר לא תוכל להרפא, asher lo suchal l'herafeh,
it says. ומדכתיב ובחרס, umidichsiv uvachares, and it says one of the
things mentioned number one is חרס, cheres, which is the dry one.
So and it also mentions in that פסוק pasuk גרב. garev. So
therefore, if one type of the word is explicitly the dry one,
גרב garev is לח, lach, is moist, and it says אשר לא
תוכל להרפא asher lo suchal l'herafeh that it won't heal. So you
see that even if it's moist, it won't heal. So how can
you say our משנה mishnah is moist and it will heal? So
the גמרא gemara says, אימא, eima, and it says it can't heal.
אלא תלתא הוו, ela tlasa havei, there are three types of גרב.
garev. דקרא יבש בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ, dikra yavesh bein mibifnim bein
mibachutz, when it's mentioned in the מומים mumim that a גרב garev
is a מום, mum, that's dry on the inside and the outside,
which can also alternatively be called חרס cheres because it's like pottery,
it's totally dry. דמתניתין, demasnissin, our משנה mishnah which says it's in
a middle category, לח מבחוץ ומבפנים lach mibachutz umibifnim is moist on
the inside and outside, and therefore it can heal, and therefore it's
in this category where you can't שחט shacht but you can bring
as a קרבן. korban. דמצרים, demitzrayim, the one in the פסוק pasuk
right that says יככה ה' בשחין מצרים ובעפלים, yakecha Hashem bishchin mitzrayim
uva'afolim, right? So the one that's mentioned in the context of the
afflictions of the Egyptians that it can't heal, יבש מבפנים ולח מבחוץ,
yavesh mibifnim velach mibachutz, it's dry on the inside and moist on
the outside, and that also would be a מום mum that you
can שחט shacht on because as you said, it cannot heal. And
how do we know that it's moist on the outside? דכתיב, dichsiv,
because it says by מצרים, mitzrayim, היה שחין אבעבועות פורח באדם ובבהמה.
haya shchin ava'buos pore'ach ba'adam uvabehema. It says sprouting. So sprouting means
like stuff is coming out of it, which means that it's moist
on the outside, but that it's hard on the inside. Something that
has to sprout from the... Right, I got it. Okay, moving on.
Either way, if it's hard on the inside, it won't heal, it's
a מום. mum. If it's moist on the inside and outside, it
could heal, and that's our משנה mishnah where if it's a temporary
מום, mum, you don't bring it as a קרבן, korban, but you
don't שחט. shacht. Now we get to the whole new category, so
let's take a look. Things that are not מומים. mumim. הזקן והחולה
והמזוהם, hazaken vehacholeh vehamizuham, the smelly and old and sick. Okay, these
are things which are not appropriate as a קרבן, korban, but not
necessarily a מום, mum, maybe not in the תמים tamim category. So
now we're going to learn where we learn this from. Is that
different than what we just had for the משנה mishnah before? We're
saying, could we just have also זקן חולה ומזוהם? zaken choleh umizuham?
We're quoting it, we're now in the גמרא. gemara. מנא הני מילי,
mena hani mili, where do I know this from? דתנו רבנן. detanu
rabanan. מן הצאן, min hatzon, it says if a person brings a
קרבן, korban, מן הצאן מן הכבשים ומן העזים יקריבו. min hatzon min
hakesavim umin ha'izim yakrivu. From the sheep, from the flock, from the
sheep, from the goats. So the from, from, from is understood to
be limiting, not all, not everything you would have brought, only a
subset from them. So what are those three limiting words throwing you?
פרט לזקן ולחולה ולמזוהם. perat lezaken ulecholeh ulemizuham. So the three things
are to exclude those three cases: old, sick, and smelly. וצריכי, u'tzrichi,
you need all three. דאי כתב רחמנא חדא, de'ei kesav rachmana chada,
if the Torah had said one, למיעוטי זקן דלא הדר ברי, lemi'utei
zaken delo hadar bari, to exclude old because you don't get better
from being old. Like they said, being old is no fun, but
it's better than the alternative, right? So that's anyway something that is
a permanent condition. אבל חולה דהדר ברי, aval choleh dehadar bari, but
if it's sick, maybe it'll get better, maybe it's not as bad,
אימא לא, eima lo, maybe that wouldn't be excluded. ואי כתב למיעוטי
חולה דלאו אורחיה, ve'ei kesav lemi'utei choleh delav orchia, if it had
just said another one, or if it had just indicated a sick,
maybe sick because that's unusual. אבל זקן דהיינו אורחיה, aval zaken dehainu
orchia, old, which everything gets old, so אימא לא, eima lo, maybe
that would not be a problem. ואי כתב רחמנא תרי, ve'ei kesav
rachmana srei, if it had just excluded two, למיעוטי הני דכחישי, lemi'utei
hani dechachishi, both old and sick are like weak. אבל מזוהם דלא
כחיש, aval mizuham delo kachish, smelly, which isn't weak at least, אימא
לא, eima lo, maybe it wouldn't be excluded. ואינמי למיעוטי מזוהם, ve'inami
lemi'utei mizuham, or the opposite, it would have excluded smelly, משום דמאיס,
mishum dema'is, because that's disgusting. אבל הני דלא מאיסי, aval hani delo
ma'isi, these are not, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe they wouldn't have
been excluded. צריכי, tzrichi, so you needed to exclude all three because
they all have different characters to them. One doesn't get better, the
other is abnormal, the other is smelly. Okay, and therefore all three
are excluded. And now we get to the category of things that
are actually involved in עבירה. aveira. ושנעבדה בו עבירה, veshene'evda bo aveira,
was used in bestiality. מנא הני מילי? mena hani mili? דתנו רבנן.
detanu rabanan. So another פסוקים, pesukim, not from the flock, but the
opening פסוק pasuk that about the עולה olah altogether. It says אדם
כי יקריב מכם קרבן מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן. adam ki
yakriv mikem korban min habehema min habakar umin hatzon. מן הבהמה, min
habehema, להוציא רובע ונרבע, lehotzi rove'a venirva, an animal used in bestiality,
whether the male or the female. מן הבקר, min habakar, from the
cattle, להוציא את הנעבד, lehotzi es hane'evad, an animal that was worshipped
as a קרבן. korban. ומן הצאן, umin hatzon, or the sheep, להוציא
את המוקצה, lehotzi es hamuktza, something which doesn't mean מוקצה muktza for
שבת, shabbos, set aside for עבודה זרה avoda zara even if it's
not actually worshipped. ומן הצאן, umin hatzon, the extra ו, vav, להוציא
את הנוגח, lehotzi es hanogei'ach, an animal that actually gored. the male
or the female, מן הבקר *Min habakar* from the cattle, להוציא את
הנעבד *lehotzi et hanevad*, את הנעבד *et hanevad*, an animal that was
worshiped, ומן הצאן *Umin hatzon* or the sheep, להוציא את המוקצה *lehotzi
et hamuktza*, something which does not mean מוקצה *muktza* for שבת *Shabbos*,
set aside for עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* even if not actually worshiped,
ומן הצאן *Umin hatzon*, the extra ו' *vav*, להוציא את הנוגח *lehotzi
et hanogeiach*, an animal that actually gored. Okay, so basically it adds
to our משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* not just bestiality, but even something that
was used as an object of worship for עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*.
So let's take a look. So first of all the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says number one, הני בדי קטולי נינהו *Hani b'dei katoli ninhu*?
You have to kill them. Not the thing that was worshiped, that's
אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah*, but but certainly the one that gored or
was used in bestiality, so what's the question about using it as
a קרבן korban. *korban*? You're supposed to stone them. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, no, that's why we say על פי עד אחד
או על פי הבעלים *Al pi ed echad o al pi habaalim*.
You only know it through one witness or through the owners, and
even though you know it as a fact, you don't actually have
it has it doesn't have the status of a שור הנסקל *Shor
haniskal*. It's not just like oh we can't prosecute but it really
is אסור *assur*. If it really was אסור *assur*, then I as
the owner would heed it if I knew that, you know once
I know its real status. It says that it doesn't get that
status unless you have a formal court case with two witnesses. And
therefore it never gets that halachic status of a שור הנסקל *Shor
haniskal*. Now we get on to, and that's all we're saying about
that. Now we get onto what everybody I think is more fascinated
with, which is the gender issues. So let's take a look. Before
we get there, can I just say something? Yes. What is the
general outlook what is most pleasing to God, לרצון *l'ratzon*, in this
set, or what human beings consider? Yeah, so I have to tell
you, and I appreciate that you raised this. What would we do
without you, Rivka? Because it's been bothering me, you know, it always
bothers me anyway when we read it in the תורה Torah *Torah*
in אמור *Emor*. It's been bothering me throughout this פרק *perek*, is
that the whole idea of perfection, I mean it's really problematic and
particularly about the sense that perfection is defined by physical externals. You
know, I mean you would think that in all this stuff around,
you know, from a religious perspective, the whole point would be to
focus not on the externals, right? האדם יראה לעיניים וה' יראה ללבב
*Ha'adam yireh la'einayim v'Hashem yireh lalivav*. You know, and speaking personally with
two kids that are, that have special needs and the whole sense
about what's normal and not normal and attitudes towards inclusion and exclusion.
You know, it's very disturbing. I mean, the best that I can
say is, it's the same about the fact that the תורה Torah,
*Torah*, why does the תורה Torah *Torah* want our בית המקדש beis
hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* to be gold and silver and look so beautiful?
I mean, that's not what true religious ideals are about, are about
that materialism. But we know that people are influenced by externals and,
you know, for some people to create a sense of oh, you
know, this represents God or for some people would like דאווענין *davening*
in like a שטיבל *shtiebel* and other people need their שול *shul*
to look a very particular way, the aesthetics, the decorum in order
to imbue a certain type of a feeling or a certain sense
of awe. So, you know, I would say that that's the way
I understand it, a concession to human nature and what people need
in order to feel that this gives them a sense of something
important and significant. And if God is a real God, then we
have to be very careful of exactly what the animals look like.
If we can give him anything, even something that looks disgusting, then
it lowers our estimation of God. But in the end, it's a
concession to human nature. That's the best I can understand, which still
is a problem because whenever you make these concessions, the problem is
okay, you make a concession, but how do you get somebody to
move beyond that also and to focus on the fact that this
is not really what is most important and what is essential. You
know, I mean you could say that that was a lot of
the effort of the נביאים *Nevi'im* was trying to tell the people
don't so pay so much attention to the קרבנות korbanot *korbanos*, that's
not what really matters, what matters more is how you treat your
fellow human being and so on. So, you know, I mean that's,
but thank you for raising it because it's definitely something that's been
very troubling, and especially you get to like old and sick. And
are we supposed to care for the old and sick, right? Well
these are animals you're going to slaughter. What? I understand, but I'm
just saying, you know, there's definitely a metaphor here that's not telling
you anything helpful. I understand. It's a, yeah, it's a, and how
about just the whole issue about like physical deformities, right? And people
that are, you know, that are a little bit different than other
people. It's a real issue. There's an issue we didn't address is
even if, I don't know if it will, let's say the animal
is physically okay, but you know, there's like some sort of mental
problem that it can't walk... No, no, no, but like a distracted
kid, right? It can't walk right because it's distracted. I don't know.
Or even a test like this. Right, what's a... Yeah, I don't
know. Most of these things have to do with the more aesthetic
and visibility, other than the ones now that are about עבירה *aveirah*,
so it's possible that wouldn't be a problem. But yeah, it definitely,
thank you, it definitely really needed to be said. It's been really
bothering me the last few days. So let's go on. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this: בשלמא טומטום tumtum במקדש לא *Bishlama tumtum
bimikdash lo*. So I understand why the טומטום *tumtum* is a problem,
you can't bring it as a קרבן korban, *korban*, because the טומטום
*tumtum* is that the genitalia are covered up. It's a male or
female, we just don't know. So I understand why you're not going
to bring it as a בכור bechor? *bechor*, דילמא נקבה היא Dilma
nekeivah hee, *dilma nekeivah hi*. Maybe it's a female. ובמדינה לא *Uvamedinah
lo*, and don't שחט *shecht* it outside the בית המקדש beis hamikdash,
*Beis HaMikdash*, דילמא זכר zachar הוא *dilma zachar hu*. Maybe it's a
male. And it has a... wait... maybe it's a male. And you
still... whatever it is that's blocking. You could, but you haven't, and
maybe it's a dangerous operation, whatever it is. Okay, so that I
get. Okay, ולית ביה מומא *V'leis bei muma* and the just... But
let's talk about the אנדרוגינוס. androgynos אנדרוגינוס בשלמא במקדש לא, Androgynos bishlama
bemikdash lo, I understand you don't bring it in the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash. why as a בכור? bechor דילמא נקבה היא, maybe it's
a female. אלא במדינה, Ela bamedinah, but outside the בית המקדש, either
way, ניהי נמי דזכר הוא, neehee nami dezachar hu, if it was
male, תעשה נקבות חריץ, te'aseh nekeivus charitz, let the female genitalia be,
even if it's a female it's not a בכור bechor altogether. If
it's a male, let the female genitalia be like a crevice, okay,
חריץ, charitz, which is the crevice is a type of a מום,
mum, וישחט עליה, veyishchat aleha, so because one of the things that
the תורה Torah says is או חרוץ, o charutz, which is an
animal which has some type of a crevice in its body, unnatural
one. So אמר אביי אמר קרא או חרוץ או שבור, amar Abaye
amar kra o charutz o shavur, crevice or broken. חרוץ דומיא דשבור,
Charutz dumya deshavur, מה שבור במקום עצם, mah shavur bemakom etzem, the
same way a break means a break at a bone, אף חרוץ
במקום עצם, af charutz bemakom etzem, it has to be in a
place where there is a bone and not in that area of
the animal where there is no bone. So therefore that's how it's
possible that we would not consider it a blemish. Again the funny
thing is even if it doesn't fit in the narrow definition of
that word in the תורה, Torah what about this generic category you
know about disfiguring things? We don't, so which is obviously the second
opinion in the משנה, Mishnah. but here it's saying that no that's
not. Again which would make you know the idea of like this
third gender from the gender identity to be very happy, we're not
calling it a מום, mum, right, it's something that's separate. But it's
interesting not calling it either a separate gender which is the last
opinion in the משנה. Mishnah. רבא אמר בלא שבור נמי לא מצית
אמרת חרוץ במקום בשר הוי מומא. Rava amar belo shavur nami lo
matzis amart charutz bemakom basar havei muma. Even without the comparison to
broken you could not say that this problem of חרוץ charutz applies
to a place without a bone. Why? אי סלקא דעתך הוי מומא,
Ei salka dachach havei muma, were it to be a blemish, כיון
דאמר גרב שחין, keivan de'amar garav shechin, we just said that גרב
garav which is a מום mum is this type of hardened you
know pottery-like whatever dried you know wart or something. So מחץ חרץ,
mechatz charatz, that actually doesn't just ride on the surface, that actually
digs into the skin. דכתיב ומראהו עמוק מן העור, Dechtiv umarehu amok
min ha'or, because it says by the leprosy, by צרעת, tzara'as, that
it's deeper than the skin and we say כמראה חמה העמוקה מן
הצל, kemarei chamah ha'amukah min hatzel, which is always a very funny
phrase, like the sun is looks deeper than the shadows, we always
assume the opposite, anyway we're not going to go there. Anyway since
it speaks about this type of a חרס cheres we assume that
that also digs in and gets into the skin and that's not
a problem, I mean and that's a problem, but why then does
it have to say גרב garav separately if anytime something goes into
the skin it's problematic? I don't know. Somehow we're making some comparison
to צרעת. tzara'as. ולכתוב רחמנא חרוץ ולא בעי גרב, Velichtov Rachmana charutz
velo ba'ei garav, so why didn't the תורה Torah just say a
crevice and not have to say this case of the wart since
this type of a wart would dig into the skin anyway? ואמינא
חרוץ דלא מאיס הוי מומא, Ve'amina charutz delo ma'is havei muma, if
a normal crevice isn't a blemish, is already a blemish, גרב דמאיס
garav dema'is כל שכן, kol shekein, how much more so would a
גרב garav which A digs into the skin and number two is
more disgusting certainly would be a blemish. So כתב רחמנא גרב למימרא
דחרוץ במקום בשר לא הוי מומא. katav Rachmana garav lemeimra decharutz bemakom
basar lo havei muma. So therefore you see from the fact that
the תורה Torah had to say גרב garav that we couldn't just
infer that that was a problem because it dug into the skin,
that a crevice normally unless it's in a place of a bone
would not be a problem. Okay so that was pretty like you
know sort of complicated but the basic פשט pshat was was that
normal this problem of חרוץ charutz was only in a place where
there's a bone so you cannot normally say that just because it
has female genitalia that it falls into the category of חרוץ. charutz.
Now the גמרא Gemara, goes on to the other opinions in the
משנה. Mishnah רבי ישמעאל אומר אין לך מום גדול מזה. Rabbi Yishmael
omer ein lecha mum gadol mizeh. כדאביי לא אמר. Ke'Abaye lo amar.
Now why does Rabbi Yishmael say that it is a מום mum
if we just got through arguing why it wasn't? So he doesn't
say like Abaye, חרוץ דומיא דשבור לא אמרינן. charutz dumya deshavur lo
amrinan. We don't say חרוץ charutz has to be like broken. Broken
is a bone, crevice is anywhere, so therefore this female genitalia counts
constitutes חרוץ charutz and therefore it's a blemish. כדרבא למה לא אמר?
KeRava lamah lo amar? He wasn't convinced by Rava's arguments, it was
a little anachronistic, anyway that would not have convinced him. Why? דילמא
היכא דלא מינכרא אבל היכא דמינכרא מום רע קרינן ביה. Dilma heicha
delo minchara aval heicha deminchara mum ra karinan bei. It says that
you know that the problem of חרוץ charutz is only by a
bone because if the problem of חרוץ charutz was anyway why did
the תורה Torah have to say גרב? garav? גרב garav is a
type of a חרוץ, charutz, okay. So he says no that's not
a problem because he would have said היכא דלא מינכרא, heicha delo
minchara, that maybe if it's in a place where it's not obvious
then a crevice wouldn't be an issue. אבל היכא דמינכרא, Aval heicha
deminchara, but if it's obvious, מום רע קרינן ביה, mum ra karinan
bei, and here it would be more visible. Okay so whatever it
is obviously it seems like Rabbi Yishmael's position makes more sense but
if you're going to call it a male it certainly would be
a מום mum for a male, okay, and that's his position so
either it is we're going to go further, I don't know if
you have to go but we think we're going to go a
little further today so we're going to hopefully catch up, luckily it's
a short דף עמוד ב. daf amud beis. Okay so he basically
says what makes sense. He says even if I'm willing to consider
it's a male, it's a male with a blemish, and therefore you
can shecht it out of the בית המקדש. So בעי רבא, bai
Rava, so רבא Rava asked מאי טעמא דרבי ישמעאל? mai ta'ama de'Rabbi
Ishmael? And when רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says it's a blemish, what's
his reasoning? So it seems his reasoning is obvious; this genitalia is
a blemish. But no, here's the question we want to ask: מכדי
פשיטא ליה, michdee pshita lei, is it obvious to him that אנדרוגינוס
בכור הוא ומומו עמו, androgynos bechor hu umumo imo, that an אנדרוגינוס
androgynos? is a male, meaning what does he think about the אנדרוגינוס?
androgynos Does he think it's definitely a male but it's a male
with this female genitalia so it's a male with a blemish? עוד
דילמא הוא אספוקי מספקא ליה, od dilma hu isfukei mistapka lei, he
doesn't know if it's male or female, and he says either way
you can eat it, right? Either it's female, then it's not a
בכור bechor at all, or it's male with a blemish and then
it's a בכור bechor with a blemish, right? ואם תמצי לומר, ve'im
timtzo lomar, and he's saying either way: אם תמצי לומר בכור הוא,
im timtzo lomar bechor hu, first of all maybe it's a female
and it's not a בכור bechor altogether, and even if it's a
male, הרי מומו עמו, harei mumo imo, it's got a blemish. Okay,
so you could, that's a reasonable position, that maybe he says, you
know, he's uncertain whether it's male or female. So גמרא Gemara says
למאי נפקא מינא, lemai nafka mina, what do I care whether it's
either way you can shecht it and eat it? What do I
care whether he calls it a non-male or it's a male with
a blemish? So the גמרא Gemara says here's the נפקא מינא: nafka
mina: למילקי עליה משום גיזה ועבודה. lemilkei alei mishum giza va'avoda. Number
one is let's say you don't shecht it and you shear it
or you work it. So if you say it might be a
female, you can't give the guy lashes because maybe it wasn't a
בכור bechor altogether. If you say it's definitely a male with a
blemish, so the blemish lets you shecht it, but it's still a
בכור bechor and until you shecht it, if you shear it or
work it, you transgress. So would you be able to definitely know
that a person had violated? Is it a definite male and he
definitely violated or not? Here's a better נפקא מינא, nafka mina, a
more relevant: אי נמי למתביה לכהן. i nami lemasvei lekohen. That's always
the question. Do I have to give it to a כהן? kohen?
I had this אנדרוגינוס androgynos animal born to me. If it's a
definite male with a מום, mum, I have to give it to
the כהן kohen and the כהן kohen shechts it. But if it
might be a female, then I say you can't prove it's yours
and therefore I get to keep it and I get to shecht
it and eat it. So there's the big נפקא מינא nafka mina
whether we say it's a doubt or a definite male. Let's take
a look. תא שמע: ta shma: רבי אילעא אומר משום רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Ilai omer mishum Rabbi Ishmael. רבי אילעא Rabbi Ilai says in
the name of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. I was wondering whether this
was the same אילעא Ilai that we had in the משנה Mishnah
before, remember אילעא Ilai and this אילעא. Ilai. There's this אילעא, Ilai,
what how was his name spelled back then? It was different, not
with a yud. אילעא, Ilai, okay, anyway, spelling sometimes change. אילעא. Ilai.
No, we had רבי אילעא Rabbi Ilai before about יהודה בר אילעא.
Yehuda bar Ilai. Yeah, that's יהודה בר אילעא, Yehuda bar Ilai, that's
yeah. So I don't know, okay anyway, let's keep it going. רבי
אילעא אומר משום רבי ישמעאל: Rabbi Ilai omer mishum Rabbi Ishmael: אנדרוגינוס
בכור הוא ומומו עמו. androgynos bechor hu umumo imo. So here he's
quoting רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and it sounds like he's saying in
a very definitive terms: it is a בכור bechor, but it has
a blemish. So גמרא, Gemara שמע מינה, shma mina, מכדי פשיטא ליה,
michdee pshita lei, you see it's obvious to him. So גמרא Gemara
says no, דילמא אם תמצי לומר קאמר. dilma im timtzo lomar kamar.
Maybe he's saying even if you say, even if you were to
say it's a בכור, bechor, it has מומו עמו, mumo imo, but
it doesn't mean we know for sure that it's a בכור, bechor,
it doesn't mean we know for sure that it's male. תא שמע:
ta shma: זכר zachar? ולא נקבה. velo nekeva. It says by an
עולה olah it has to be male, so we say not a
female. כשאמר למטה זכר kishe'omar lemata zachar and then it says again
in the פסוק pasuk male. שאין תלמוד לומר, she'ein talmud lomar, it
didn't have to tell me male, you've already told me that an
עולה olah has to be male. מה תלמוד לומר, ma talmud lomar,
why does it say? להוציא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, lehotzi tumtum ve'androgynos, to exclude
טומטום and אנדרוגינוס androgynos which are not fully male or definitely male.
מאן, man, now who's this going like? אילימא תנא קמא, ileima tana
kama, if it's our first תנא tana of our משנה mishna that
said it's not a מום, mum,
so nevertheless ספיקא הוא. sveika hu. He still says that an אנדרוגינוס
androgynos. is a doubt, right? And therefore you can't bring it as
a קרבן. It's not a מום mum but it's not necessarily male.
ואתי קרא למיעוטי ספיקא? va'ati kra l'imutei sveika? You wouldn't need a
פסוק pasuk to exclude a case of a doubt. Now why not?
I mean תוספות Tosafot says of course, you know, you need a
פסוק pasuk to tell you how to deal with doubt. So תוספות
Tosafot says here's the difference. If it's a case that might come
up from time to time and there might be a doubt what
the case is, then the תורה Torah might tell you here's what
you do in a case when you're not certain. But here the
question is not something that's different from time to time, it's the
category of אנדרוגינוס. androgynos? How do we treat the category of אנדרוגינוס?
androgynos, That's a הלכה halakhic question, that's not a fact question. So
the תורה Torah might tell you what do you do in a
case where there's a factual doubt because we're human and we have
factual doubts. But if the question about the הלכה, halakhic, the legal
question of how do you define אנדרוגינוס, androgynos figure it out. I'm
not going to tell you, "Oh, I God don't know whether it's
male or female and here's what you do because it's a doubt,"
okay? So if if you have a legal question of it's a
doubt, the תורה Torah is not going to be addressing that legal
question. So therefore it's saying if according to the תנא קמא Tana
Kama that אנדרוגינוס androgynos is a doubt, so if that's true, the
תורה would not tell you oh because it's doubtfully הלכה halakhically how
we categorize it don't treat it as a male. You figure out
if it's male or female and then you figure out which category
it's in. The תורה would not have to tell you that. Okay,
so therefore it cannot be תנא קמא. Tana Kama. אלא רבנן בתראי,
ela rabbanan basrai, how about the last רבנן? rabbanan? Remember the last
one said it's not, it's definitely not a בכור, bechor right? It's
a... separate gender. So maybe they are the ones that you needed
the פסוק pasuk to exclude it based on זכר? zachar So the
גמרא says, No, מחד קרא נפקא. mechad kra nafak. התם גבי בכור
חד קרא הוא
דכתיב.
hatam gabei bechor chad
kra hu dechtiv.
Then one פסוק pasuk would have been
enough. How do I know one פסוק pasuk would have been enough?
Because by בכור bechor it doesn't say זכר zachar twice. By בכור
bechor. it only says זכר zachar, once. And nevertheless, we know, we
have seen in the משנה that there's an opinion that says אנדרוגינוס
androgynos? is completely excluded from בכור. bechor It's not, it's a separate
gender, it's not זכר, zachar it's completely excluded. So if it were
that opinion that even by בכור bechor excludes it completely, it's a
completely separate gender, why by other קרבנות did you need two פסוקים?
psukim? If by בכור bechor. we excluded it just based on one
זכר zachar. because it's not male. אלא פשיטא, Ella pshita, it must
be רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. It must be that it's רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael who says that it's a male with a מום. mum.
אי אמרת בשלמא רבי ישמעאל מיפשט פשיטא ליה, Ee amart bishlama Rabbi
Yishmael mipshat pshita lei, if it's obvious to him that it's a
male with a מום, mum, היינו דאיצטריך קרא למעוטי, hainu de’itztarech kra
le’moutei, then you understand why you needed the פסוקים psukim to exclude
it. Because then I would have said, oh, well it is male,
it just has a blemish. So maybe even if I can't bring
it as a קרבן, maybe if I sanctify it, it has קדושה
kedusha and so on. So therefore you need פסוקים psukim to tell
you, no, even though it's a male, because of this problem, it
doesn't have any קדושת קרבן kedushat korban if you try to sanctify
it. That's what I would say. אלא אי אמרת מספקא ליה, Ella
ee amart mesafeka lei, but again, if it's possibly not even a
male, איצטריך קרא למעוטי ספיקא? itztarech kra le’moutei safeika? Would you get
the point of why would I need a תורה to have addressed
it if it's just the issue of its doubtful status? So the
גמרא says, so anyway, so they're trying to prove that according to
since you need פסוקים psukim to exclude it, the only reason you
would need two פסוקים psukim to exclude it is if it would
have been a definite male with a blemish. And the גמרא in
the end rejects this and says, no, לעולם רבנן בתראי, le'olam Rabbanan
basrai, it really could be the latter רבנן Rabbanan that says that
it's a separate gender. וגבי בכור תרתי קראי כתיבי. vegabei bechor tarti
kraei ktivi. הזכר והזכרים. Hazachar ve’hazacharim. And even though it's a separate
gender, you need two פסוקים. psukim. Okay, and it does say two
פסוקים psukim by בכור. bechor It says two פסוקים psukim by, what
do you call them? By the second. Anyway, we're about to wrap
up. By even by בכור bechor, it has two פסוקים. psukim. It
says the פסוק pasuk רש״י Rashi quotes. One is הזכר תקדיש Hazachar
takdish and אשר יהיה לך הזכרים לה׳, asher yihiye lecha hazacharim l'Hashem,
which means the following: It might be a separate gender, but because
it is a separate gender, it's not necessarily excluded by one mention
of the word זכר. zachar Right? Maybe זכר zachar is enough? You
know, maybe זכר zachar is only excluding the exact opposite gender, the
female. But something that's the middle gender maybe isn't excluded. Our only
question was that if you only needed one פסוק pasuk by בכור,
bechor why you needed two פסוקים psukim by the other animals to
exclude the separate gender? And our answer is: No, we have two
פסוקים psukim by בכור bechor. as well. It says זכר zachar twice
by בכור. So it could be it's a separate gender, but one
word זכר zachar might not be enough. זכר zachar might only exclude
female. You need the separate זכר to exclude even this middle gender.
Okay, so the upshot of all of this was that we don't
know, according to the first position doesn't know if it's male or
female. The second position says even if it's male, it has a
blemish. What we don't know is whether that second position also has
the doubt of whether it's male or female or not or will
definitely call it a male with a blemish. Right? Or the third
position says it's a completely separate gender. And we're going to pick
up on that third position when we return and again the interesting
point I think that תוספות Tosafot makes, which is that the פסוקים
psukim would need to tell you how you deal with a doubt
in facts, but if there's a doubt in law, then the פסוקים
psukim aren't going to tell you how to deal with the fact
that it is a doubt, it'll either be one or the other
and that's for you to figure out. But we do have this
remaining question about how do we conceive of אנדרוגינוס? Do we have
a doubt whether it's male or female? Do we consider it to
be a male with a מום? mum? You could also say it's
a female with a מום, mum, but why that possibility isn't being
raised? I think it's because in general, and I was also waiting
for somebody to object to this, you know, in general about comparing
the whole idea of female genitalia to a חריץ. charitz. You know,
there's a very common way about thinking about female as the non-
the absence of male. Right? As lacking male genitalia. Thomas? Why? Exactly.
So I think it's for that reason, I think it's for that
reason that we don't consider it to be a female with a
מום. mum. Once it has male genitalia, right, the only possibility is
it can't be a female anymore because it has male genitalia. But
it's possible that it's a male with a מום mum and that's
a possibility, or that it's a third gender. So that we will
continue with tomorrow.